{"tossups": [{"question": "This event led the sitting president to declare an end to the \u201ctermination\u201d policy. John Trudell was the spokesperson and radio operator for the perpetrators of this event, which was organized by Adam Fortunate Eagle. Unthanksgiving Day is a memorial dedicated to this event, whose location was used as the starting point for \u201cThe Longest Walk\u201d by AIM. Coast Guard blockades cut off supplies during, for ten points, what 19-month-long protest by Native American activists on an island in San Francisco Bay?", "answer": "American Indian Movement\u2019s (or AIM\u2019s)<b> occupation of Alcatraz</b> Island (or<b> occupation of Alcatraz</b> Prison, etc.; accept equivalents for \u201coccupation;\u201d prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This royal figure was forced to testify after Sir William Gordon-Cummming sued for slander as part of a baccarat scandal. Jean-Baptiste Sipido was acquitted by a Belgian court due to his youth after he tried to assassinate this man over the Boer War. This monarch died in the midst of a constitutional crisis that, after his death, led the House of Lords losing its veto power. For ten points, name this son of Victoria who was succeeded by George V after his 1910 death.", "answer": "<b> Edward VII</b> (accept<b> Albert Edward</b>; prompt on Edward)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A company from this country built the<em> Phoenix</em>, led by James George Shields. George Simpson helped negotiate an agreement with an official from this country over clashes at Redoubt Saint Dionysius. After a treaty with the Hudson\u2019s Bay Company, Fort Langley and Fort Victoria produced wheat that was sold to this nation. Fur traders from this country were based at Fort Ross in California. Ferdinand Wrangel was an administrator from this country, whose colonial possessions included a capital city at Sitka. For ten points, name this country that sold Alaska to the US.", "answer": "<b> Russia</b>n Empire", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This figure calls communism a \u201cphantom\u201d as the narrator of Robert Coover\u2019s<em> The Public Burning</em>. This man\u2019s vice president wrote<em> The Canfield Decision</em>, a novel in which America in 1983 has been taken over by liberal Zionists. A non-fiction work about this man\u2019s administration described the roles of John Ehrlichman and H.R. Haldeman, advisors of this man. For ten points, name this subject of Bob Woodward and Carl Bernstein\u2019s<em> All the President\u2019s Men</em>, published in 1974 just months before this president\u2019s resignation.", "answer": "Richard<b> Nixon</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In studying this psychological phenomenon, James Marcia identified \u201cexploration\u201d and \u201ccommitment\u201das two crucial elements. This quality can experience both \u201cdiffusion\u201d and \u201cforeclosure.\u201d Martin Luther\u2019s conflict between being a good son and a good monk prompted a stress of this concept according to Erik Erikson\u2019s<em> Young Man Luther</em>, which described 8 stages of development for this concept. For ten points, name this psychological concept, one\u2019s distinct personality, whose failure to develop may cause a \u201ccrisis.\u201d", "answer": "<b> identity</b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {}, {"question": "Timothy Snyder claims that the death toll of this event has been exaggerated by a factor of 3, and that its perpetrators made no class-based discrimination so that it would not be labeled a genocide. As part of this event, \u201cblack boards\u201d listing non-conforming enemies of the state were published outside villages. Lazar Kaganovich helped orchestrate this event by ordering collectivization and impossible grain export quotas. Well over 2 million people died in, for ten points, what 1932-33 genocidal disaster in Ukraine?", "answer": "<b> Holodomor</b> (prompt on descriptions of a Ukrainian famine)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Although he was initially skeptical of natural selection, this scientist later defended the theory in his <em>Critique of the Theory of Evolution</em>. This scientist\u2019s student, Alfred Sturtevant, published the first genetic map. This man, who established the biology department at Caltech after many years of work at Columbia University, won the Nobel Prize in Medicine for determining the role of chromosomes in genetics. For ten points, name this biologist who studied fruit flies.", "answer": "Thomas Hunt<b> Morgan</b>", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {"question": "The Mackinnon-Sclater Road spanned this country and was replaced in the early 20th century by a railway described as the \u201cLunatic Line.\u201d This country\u2019s city of Port Florence was developed as the western terminus of that railway; the city is now named Kisumu. The construction of a bridge for that railway over this country\u2019s Tsavo River was plagued by a pair of man-eating lions that killed dozens of workers. The Nandi people violently opposed British construction projects in, for ten points, what East African country that Teddy Roosevelt rode across on the Uganda Railway from its port city of Mombasa?", "answer": "<b> Kenya</b> (accept British<b> Kenya</b>; accept British<b> East Africa Protectorate</b> before \u201cEast Africa\u201d is mentioned) Page 3", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "In July 2016, one of this league\u2019s players was fined after accepting a Player of the Month award wearing an inside-out black shirt to protest police brutality; that fine, and others for wearing all-black in protest, were rescinded by this league\u2019s president, Lisa Borders. Tamika Catchings and the rest of this league\u2019s Indiana Fever knelt during the national anthem before a 2016 playoff game against the Phoenix Mercury. For ten points, name this female professional basketball league.", "answer": "<b> Women\u2019s National Basketball Association</b> (or<b> WNBA</b>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "The perpetrator of this crime spent just five weeks in prison before his execution, as told in the papers of warden L.F. Chapman. The term \u201cdeath row\u201d was first used regarding the housing of the perpetrator of this crime, who shouted \u201cToo many people are starving,\u201d a possible reference to the chronic stomach pain he faced as a bricklayer. According to legend, Anton Cermak said \u201cI\u2019m glad it was me instead of you\u201d after he was hit by a lethal stray bullet during, for ten points, what failed attempt on the life of the president-elect in 1933?", "answer": "<b> attempted assassination</b> of<b> F</b>ranklin<b> Roosevelt</b> (accept<b> FDR</b> in place of Franklin Roosevelt; accept equivalents such as<b> shooting FDR</b> as long as they don\u2019t explicitly indicate he died; accept<b> assassination</b> or<b> murder</b> of Anton<b> Cermak</b> before his name is mentioned; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Over nine million acres of land in this state was given away by the terms of the Kinkaid Act. In the late 19th century, cowboys discovered the ease of ranging cattle in this state\u2019s Sand Hills. A fur trapper traveling to a rendezvous discovered a prominent formation in this state whose distinctive pointed shape made it a landmark on the Oregon Trail. Chimney Rock can be found in, for ten points, what state where Pony Express highways were built along the Platte River?", "answer": "<b> Nebraska</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "According to legend, this man lifted up a door as a bridge to allow his men to cross a moat in the Battle of Khaybar. This man reluctantly ordered Malik al-Ashtar to pull back his forces, most of whom refused to fight when enemy soldiers placed the Quran on a spear. This man, who led forces against Mu\u2019awiyah at the Battle of Siffin, was killed by Ibn Muljam, a Khajirite at the Great Mosque of Kufa. The First Fitna was faced by this man, who was traditionally cursed by his successors, the Ummayads. Uthman was succeded by, for ten points, what fourth and last of the Rightly-Guided Caliphs?", "answer": "<b> Ali</b> ibn Abi Talib", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man was opposed by the Community Front in Defense of Land after he announced plans to build an airport in San Salvador Atenco. This man\u2019s Secretary of Foreign Affairs, Jorge Castaneda, reversed his country\u2019s policy of not commenting on the legitimacy of other governments, the (+) Estrada Doctrine. This non-American announced a mock bid for the 2020 US presidency as part of a series of comedic attacks on Donald Trump. When this man defeated (*)</b> Francisco Labastida, he became the first candidate in 71 years to defeat a PRI candidate. For ten points, name this man who served as President of Mexico from 2000 to 2006.", "answer": "Vicente<b> Fox</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>The punishment in this case was overturned by Grafton Green because it was applied by a judge, rather than a jury. In a speech stating \u201cthere is never a duel with the truth,\u201dDudley Field Malone argued for the inclusion of academic evidence into this trial, which</b> <b>may have been organized by George (+)</b> <b>Rappleyea to bring publicity to the town of</b> <b>Dayton. This case was covered by the</b><em><b> Baltimore Sun</b></em><b> by H.L. Mencken, who left before its prosecutor was questioned about his (*) </b> belief in the Bible. For ten points, name this 1925 court case in which Clarence Darrow sparred with William Jennings Bryan over evolution", "answer": "<b> Scopes</b> Monkey Trial (or State of Tennessee vs. John Thomas<b> Scopes</b>; accept<b> Monkey</b> Trial) Page 11", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>During this conflict, Operation Carlota brought aid to one side just in time for the Battle of Quifangondo. After the CIA were found to be influencing this conflict through Operation IA Feature, the Clark Amendment barred the United States from further intervention.</b> <b>This conflict was described as (+)</b> <b>\u201cCuba\u2019s Vietnam\u201d thanks to Fidel Castro\u2019s support for</b> <b>Agostinho Neto. The death of Jonas (*)</b> Savimbi helped end this conflict, which began shortly after a country gained independence from Portugal. For ten points, name this African civil war fought between UNITA and the MPLA that determined control of Luanda.", "answer": "<b> Angola</b>n<b> Civil</b> War", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>In Japan, one of these figures in the form of a monk safeguards the souls of hell-beings and children and is named Ksitigarbha. Another one of these figures supposedly had eleven faces and names a dharani sutra translated by Xuanzang. One of these figures who is</b> <b>depicted with a (+)</b> <b>thousand arms is named Guanyin in China based on a disputed</b> <b>translation of the name Avalokitesvara. Empress Wu Zetian claimed she was an incarnation of one of these figures named (*)</b> Maitreya, who will teach the true dharma after the disappearance of Gautama\u2019s teachings. For ten points, name these enlightened beings who assist others in the path toward nirvana in Buddhism.", "answer": "<b> Bodhisattva</b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "<b>This man delayed his resignation as Prime Minister in the hopes that his rival, Henry Campbell-Bannerman, would be removed from his post in the Relugas Affair. This man was appointed Chief Secretary of Ireland, where his enforcement of the Crimes Act earned him the epithet (+) \u201cBloody.\u201d As Prime Minister, this man was nearly dragged into war when Russian ships fired on British fishermen at Dogger Bank, and as Foreign Secretary, he wrote a public letter to Lord (*) </b> Rothschild in 1917 favoring the creation of a \u201cnational home.\u201d For ten points, name this British politician, the namesake of a Declaration supporting the creation of Israel.", "answer": "Arthur<b> Balfour</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>One side in this battle attempted to use Belgian civilians as human shields in the defense of Joe\u2019s Bridge. Brian Horrock\u2019s XXX Corps [thirtieth \u201ccore\u201d] attempted to meet up with</b> <b>Polish troops at Driel by advancing through Highway 69, or (+)</b> <b>\u201cHell\u2019s Highway,\u201d during</b> <b>this battle, but they failed to relieve Allied forces pocketed at Oosterbeek. The phrase \u201ca (*)</b> bridge too far\u201d arose from this battle, in which the 1st and 82nd Airborne Divisions failed to secure a path across the Waal and Rhine Rivers at Nijmegen [nye-may-hen] and Arnhem. For ten points, name this failed 1944 paratrooper operation in the Netherlands.", "answer": "Operation<b> Market-Garden</b> (accept Operation<b> Garden</b> alone, but not Market alone, throughout the question) (10) <b>A kingdom in this modern country started a war by sending a box full of dung to</b> <b>another country instead of the hair of a white elephant. A kingdom of a \u201cMillion Elephants and White Parasols\u201d existed in this modern country; Fa Ngum [fa num] founded that</b> <b>empire, Lan (+)</b> <b>Xang [lan san]. Prince Phetsarath was the first prime minister of this</b> <b>country, which was led after independence by King Sisavang Vong. Operation Steel Tiger targeted troops in this country in an effort to close off the (*) </b> Ho Chi Minh Trail. The CIA\u2019s\u201cSecret War\u201d in this country involved training thousands of Hmong soldiers. For ten points, name this landlocked Southeast Asian country that was heavily bombed during America\u2019s war with its eastern neighbor, Vietnam. ANSWER:<b> Laos</b> (or the<b> Lao People\u2019s Democratic Republic</b>; accept<b> Muang Lao</b>)  (1) <b>Sir Thomas Wriothesley commemorated the birth of this king\u2019s first son in</b> <b>the Westminster Tournament Roll. This king passed a Statute of Wills allowing landholders to choose who attained their land after death for the first time. This man,</b> <b>who declared that the English king was (+)</b> <b>also the King of Ireland and passed a</b> <b>series of laws that annexed Wales, was protested by a group of roughly 40,000 people in Yorkshire during the (*)</b> Pilgrimage of Grace, which opposed this man\u2019s dissolution of the monasteries. Thomas Cromwell and Thomas More advised, for ten points, what king of England who broke away from the Catholic Church? ANSWER:<b> Henry VIII</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}